today I want to share with you my secret
sauce I have been making educational
videos and programming courses for more
than six years now and on those years as
you might have seen we have talked about
the new technologies blockchain AI data
structures algorithms and in general
concepts that aren't easy to understand
because of this I always get questions
on how I study all those Concepts and
how I am then able to explain them and
that is what I want to share with you my
secret sauce the reason why I have been
able to learn everything I wanted the
reason why I can explain it easily is
the Feynman technique the Feynman
technique is also the reason why
studying and learning does not feel like
a chore to me it's just fun the Feynman
technique is named after Richard Feynman
a Nobel Prize winner physicist whose
nickname was the great explainer Feynman
was the absolute champ of explanations
he could explain really complex subjects
in an engaging and fun way using simple
language and lots of real world
analogies his enthusiasm when explaining
science was contagious now oxygen for
instance in the air would like to be
next to carbon and if they get in near
each other they snap together
if you can get it faster by heating it
up somehow somewhere somehow they come
close enough to the carbon and snap in
and that gives a lot of jiggly motion
which might hit some other atoms making
those go faster so they can climb up and
bump against other
carbon atoms and they jiggle and they
make mothers jiggle and you get a
terrible catastrophe that catastrophe is
a fire
he believed that we don't need any kind
of talent to understand hard Concepts
USB of an ordinary person by studying
hard would get to be able to imagine
these things like I imagine of course I
was an ordinary person who studied hard
there's no Miracle people it just
happens they got interested in this
thing and they learned all this stuff
they're just people
there's no Talent or special miracle
ability to understand quantum mechanics
or Miracle ability
to imagine electromagnetic fields that
comes without practice and reading and
learning and study so if you say you
take an ordinary person who's willing to
devote a great deal of time and study
and work and thinking and Mathematics
and timeline then he's become a
scientist
and he also believed that the best way
to know if you have really understood a
concept is to explain it to somebody
else which brings me to the Feynman
technique the Feynman technique is a
loop something you do over and over
again until you have complete
understanding of what you're trying to
learn and it is divided in four steps
step one pick a topic or a concept you
want to learn and do some research on it
watch a video read the documentation a
couple of chapters of a book Etc Step 2
write down an explanation of that
concept but try to explain that concept
to someone younger than you to a child
with a short attention span and a
smaller vocabulary the reason why is
because people usually think they
understand a concept but in reality they
just remember the name of things and
they use fancy words they don't even
understand as Feynman said knowing the
name of something and knowing something
is very different step 3 identify gaps
in your knowledge after you're done
explaining in the concept find the
places in your explanation where you
relied on fancy words or use over
complicated language if a child is not
able to understand those words that
means that you didn't make it simple
enough and that might mean that you are
just repeating things you read rather
than explaining the concepts like a
curious child that is always asking why
is this hot why is this dark or why is
this red challenge your assumptions by
asking why these will expose even more
gaps in your knowledge and will make you
dig even deeper in understanding you may
know how something works and may be able
to explain it but do you really know why
it works or what is making it work step
4 do more research after you identify
the password your knowledge is a bit
shaky the price where you are relying on
complicated terms the parts that aren't
simple enough or the parts where you
can't answer the question why do even
more research to try to answer those why
questions to simplify your explanations
and to replace complicated terms and
ideas with easy to understand and
analogies then go back to step 2 which
is writing the explanation again but
this time fill in the gaps simplified
things and provide a background
explanations on the why of things then
go to step 3 and 4 rinse and repeat
until there are no more gaps and you
feel like you can explain the concept to
a 7 year old that's it that's the fine
man technique trust me when I tell you
it is incredibly effective and it will
help you really understand a concept
rather than to just memorize it let's
put the Feynman technique in action with
a concept like blockchain that not many
people explain well or understand step
one we decide we want to learn about
blockchains so we do some research on it
after a bit of research we sort of know
what it is so we move to step number two
we try to write an explanation for it
the first draft of our explanation might
say that a blockchain is a decentralized
distributed Ledger used to record
immutable information step number three
let's try to find gaps in our knowledge
are we using complicated words yes this
centralized distributed Ledger and
immutable will a child understand them
no step number four we do more research
to understand what is decentralized what
is distributed what is immutable and
what is a ledger and back to step number
two we try to explain blockchain again
but this time with easier words maybe
now we say that a blockchain is a shared
database that everyone has access to
where information cannot be deleted only
written that's better we can repeat
steps 3 and 4 and maybe come up with an
even easier explanation using analogies
that even a child can understand maybe
we end up with an explanation that says
that a blockchain is a group of friends
with the notebooks and pens in their
hands these friends are writing down
something they care about like their
scores on their favorite video game to
make sure no one cheats or makes a
mistake after every game they all ride
the score in their own personal notebook
at the same time and compare notebooks
to make sure all information is the same
and because they are using pens and not
pencils after the score is written it
cannot be erased after this explanation
a child might ask how do all these
friends talk to each other which will
make us go to step number four where we
will have to do research about
peer-to-peer communication to go back to
step number two to explain to the child
that the friends are all talking on the
phone and so on and so on I hope that by
now you can see how incredibly helpful
this Feynman technique is apart from
being very effective and useful it's
also really fun it makes the act of
learning into a quest it also turns
learning into a creative exercise where
we have to be creative to come up with
analogies and explain things to an
imaginary child usually learning is
always input input input and that's why
people get bored with the Feynman
technique it becomes an input and output
game I hope that you use it in your
studies and I hope that it helps you as
much as it helped me before I go I'll
leave you with two quotes by Mr fireman
himself nobody ever figures out what
life is all about and it doesn't matter
explore the word nearly everything is
really interesting if you go into it
deeply enough study hard what interests
you the most in the most undisciplined
irreverent and original manner possible
and that's it for this video if you
found it helpful please like it share it
with your friends and subscribe to the
channel and if you would like to check
out the programming courses that I made
with explanations that follow the
Feynman technique please click the link
below where you can take free courses on
JavaScript python react react native go
Dart flutter and many others all for
free click the link below and I will see
you there anjana comes see you on the
next one bye